A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files, 1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files 1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.562
This collection consists of 12,400 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred to the library in December 1956.
Scope and Content Information
These files constitute the major record series generated by the president of the University of Virginia. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office.
Architectural drawing of the landscaping for the maintainance and geological survey building grounds and a smaller architectural drawing of The Lawn Tree Planting Diagram are present.
Of interest is the file "Segregation" in Box 28, which is almost entirely concerned with the admission of Gregory Swanson, the first African American student at the University.
Contents List
- General Files, 1950
  - "A" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 1)
  - Air Forces 1950 (Box 1)
  - Airport (Milton) (empty) 1950 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Office 1950 (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education (General) 1950 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors 1950 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1950 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions - "A" 1950 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions - "B" 1950 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions - "C" 1950 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions - "D" 1950 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions - "E" 1950 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions - "F" 1950 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions - "G" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "H" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "I" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "J" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "K" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "L" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "Mc" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "M" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "N" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "O" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "P" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "Q" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "R" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "S" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "T" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "U" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "V" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "W" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions - "X -Y - Z" 1950 (Box 2)
  - Army - General 1950 (Box 2)
  - Army ROTC - Transportation Corps 1950 (Box 2)
  - Army ROTC - Medical 1950 (Box 2)
  - Art and Architecture 1950 (Box 2)
  - Art Commission 1950 (Box 2)
  - Association of American Colleges 1950 (Box 3)
  - Association of American Universities 1950 (Box 3)
  - Association of Land-Grant Colleges 1950 (Box 3)
  - Association of Virginia Colleges 1950 (Box 3)
  - Astronomy 1950 (Box 3)
  - Athletics 1950 (Box 3)
  - Athletics - National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) 1950 (Box 3)
  - Athletics - Commonwealth Day 1950 (Box 3)
  - Athletics - Intra-murals 1950 (Box 4)
  - Attorney General 1950 (Box 4)
  - Auditor of Public Accounts 1950 (Box 4)
  - "Ba - Bl" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 4)
  - "Bm - Bz" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 4)
  - Biology 1950 (Box 5)
  - Biology - Blandy Farm 1950 (Box 5)
  - Biology - Mountain Lake 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Chemistry 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Electricity 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Emergency Housing 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Emergency Housing, Copeley Hill 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Fraternity Housing 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Geology Department 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Mirador 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Roads 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Scott Stadium 1950 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds - Telephone System 1950 (Box 5)
  - Building Program - General 1950 (Box 5)
  - Building Program - Academic Building 1950 (Box 5)
  - Building Program - Architects and Engineers 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Chemistry 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Contracts 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Convalescent Children's Home 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Engineering 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Geological Survey Building 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Law Department 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Life Science Building 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Medical Buildings 1950 (Box 6)
  - Building Program - Men's Dormitories 1950 (Box 7)
  - Building Program - Power Plant and Heating Mains 1950 (Box 7)
  - Building Program - Natural Resources Building 1950 (Box 7)
  - Building Program - Physics 1950 (Box 7)
  - Building Program - Shops 1950 (Box 7)
  - Building Program - Student Activities Building 1950 (Box 7)
  - Building Program - "V" Club Building 1950 (Box 7)
  - Building Program - Women's Dormitory 1950 (Box 7)
  - Bursar's office 1950 (Box 7)
  - Byrd, Senator H. F. 1950 (Box 7)
  - "Ca - Ck" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 8)
  - "Cl - Cz" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 8)
  - Cap and Gown Order Blanks 1950 (Box 8)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace 1950 (Box 8)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching 1950 (Box 8)
  - Catalogues 1950 (Box 8)
  - Cavalier Daily 1950 (Box 8)
  - Chemistry 1950 (Box 8)
  - Classics 1950 (Box 8)
  - Commerce and Economics 1950 (Box 8)
  - Committees - Academic Legislation 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Administrative 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Algernon Sydney Sullivan Award 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Board of Visitors 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Bookstore (Cooperative) 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Cabell Hall 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Calendar 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Cemetery 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Chapel 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Chaperones' 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Citizens Committee on Displaced Persons (folder empty) 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Class Attendance 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Classroom Assignments (Committee file) (see Schedule and Classroom Assignments Committee) 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - College Policy 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Committee to Confer on Disposition of Million Dollars Appropriated by Legislature for Academic Building 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Curriculum 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Dean of Students Office Interim Committee 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Degree Voting Procedure Committee 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Development Fund - Faculty Advisory 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Draft Deferment for ROTC Students 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Extension Advisory 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Faculty Housing 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Faculty Student 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Foreign Service 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Gardens 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Graduate 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Hospital Executive 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Institute of Public Affairs Advisory 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Inter-departmental Committee on Combined Degrees 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Liberal Arts 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Library 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Local Building 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Lower Division 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Medical School Building 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Miscellaneous Committees 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - New Buildings 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Overseas Schools 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Patent Policy 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Post-War College 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Preparation of Students for Government Service (folder empty) 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - President's Committee of Ladies 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Processions 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Public Occasions 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Publications 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Radio Committee 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Research Committee 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Rushton Seminars 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Schedule and Classroom Assignments 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Service Fellowships and Scholarships 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Student Union 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - Tres 1950 (Box 9)
  - Committees - University of Virginia Press 1950 (Box 9)
  - Conservation Commission 1950 (Box 9)
  - Convocation 1950 (Box 9)
  - "D" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 10)
  - Darden, Mr. and Mrs. 1950 (Box 10)
  - Assistant Dean's Office 1950 (Box 10)
  - Dean Ferguson 1950 (Box 10)
  - Dean Hollingsworth 1950 (Box 10)
  - Dean Lewis 1950 (Box 10)
  - Dean Newman's Office 1950 (Box 10)
  - Combined Degree 1950 (Box 10)
  - Education Degree 1950 (Box 10)
  - Development Fund 1950 (Box 11)
  - "E" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 11)
  - Education - General 1950 (Box 11)
  - Alumni Board - General Correspondence 1950 (Box 11)
  - Alumni Board - Meetings 1950 (Box 11)
  - Alumni Board - Contingent Fund 1950 (Box 11)
  - Alumni Board - Treasurer 1950 (Box 11)
  - Engineering Department 1950 (Box 12)
  - English 1950 (Box 12)
  - Extension Division 1950 (Box 12)
  - "F" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 12)
  - Founder's Day 1950 (Box 12)
  - Fraternities 1950 (Box 12)
  - Faculty 1950 (Box 13)
  - Foreign Affairs 1950 (Box 13)
  - Fletcher, R. R. 1950 (Box 13)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships - Fulbright 1950 (Box 13)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships - Bayly-Tiffany 1950 (Box 13)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships - Rhodes 1950 (Box 13)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships - Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 13)
  - Finals 1950 (Box 13)
  - Food Services 1950 (Box 13)
  - Forestry 1950 (Box 13)
  - Forestry - Seward Forest 1950 (Box 13)
  - "G" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 14)
  - General Education Board 1950 (Box 14)
  - Geography 1950 (Box 14)
  - Geology 1950 (Box 14)
  - Germanic Languages 1950 (Box 14)
  - Gifts to the University 1950 (Box 14)
  - Governor's Office 1950 (Box 14)
  - Graduate Department 1950 (Box 15)
  - "Ha - He" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 15)
  - "Hf - Hz" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 15)
  - Hildreth, W. S. 1950 (Box 15)
  - History 1950 (Box 15)
  - History Commission - World War II 1950 (Box 15)
  - Honors Courses 1950 (Box 15)
  - Honor System 1950 (Box 15)
  - Housing 1950 (Box 15)
  - "I" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 15)
  - India Conference 1950 (Box 16)
  - Institute of International Education 1950 (Box 16)
  - Institute of Public Affairs 1950 (Box 16)
  - Insurance 1950 (Box 16)
  - Invitations - "A" 1950 (Box 16)
  - Invitations - "B" 1950 (Box 16)
  - Invitations - "C" 1950 (Box 16)
  - Invitations - "D" 1950 (Box 16)
  - Invitations - "E" 1950 (Box 16)
  - Invitations - "F" 1950 (Box 16)
  - Invitations - "G" 1950 (Box 16)
  - Invitations - "H" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "I" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "J" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "K" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "L" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "M" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "N" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "O" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "P" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "Q" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "R" 1950 (Box 17)
  - Invitations - "S" 1950 (Box 18)
  - Invitations - "T" 1950 (Box 18)
  - Invitations - "U" 1950 (Box 18)
  - Invitations - "V" 1950 (Box 18)
  - Invitations - "W" 1950 (Box 18)
  - Invitations - "X - Y - Z" 1950 (Box 18)
  - "J" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 18)
  - Japan International Christian University 1950 (Box 18)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1950 (Box 18)
  - "K" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 19)
  - "L" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 19)
  - Law Department 1950 (Box 19)
  - Lectures - General 1950 (Box 19)
  - Lectures - Page-Barbour 1950 (Box 19)
  - Legal Matters (W. A. Perkins, Attorney) 1950 (Box 20)
  - Legislative Program 1950 (Box 20)
  - Library 1950 (Box 20)
  - Library - Board of Alderman 1950 (Box 20)
  - Library - McGregor Library 1950 (Box 20)
  - Library - Taylor Room 1950 (Box 20)
  - Loan Funds 1950 (Box 20)
  - Lower Division of the College 1950 (Box 20)
  - "Ma - Me" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 21)
  - "Mf - Mz" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 21)
  - "Mc" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 21)
  - Madison Hall 1950 (Box 21)
  - Mary Washington College 1950 (Box 21)
  - Mary Washington Dockets 1950 (Box 21)
  - Marine Corps 1950 (Box 22)
  - Medical Department 1950 (Box 22)
  - Medical Department - Hospital 1950 (Box 22)
  - Medical Department - Nursing School 1950 (Box 22)
  - Medical Department - Student Health 1950 (Box 22)
  - Mathematics 1950 (Box 22)
  - Military - Miscellaneous (see also Army, Navy, Marine Corps, etc.) 1950 (Box 23)
  - Samuel Miller Fund 1950 (Box 23)
  - Music 1950 (Box 23)
  - "N" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 23)
  - National Association of State Universities 1950 (Box 23)
  - National Commission on Accrediting 1950 (Box 23)
  - National Education Association 1950 (Box 24)
  - National Science Foundation 1950 (Box 24)
  - Navy 1950 (Box 24)
  - Naval ROTC 1950 (Box 24)
  - Naval ROTC - printed and mimeographed communications 1950 (Box 24)
  - Newcomb, J. L. 1950 (Box 24)
  - "O" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 24)
  - Oak Ridge 1950 (Box 24)
  - "P" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 24)
  - Personnel 1950 (Box 24)
  - Personnel and Placement Office 1950 (Box 24)
  - Philadelphia Affairs 1950 (Box 25)
  - Philosophy 1950 (Box 25)
  - Photographs 1950 (Box 25)
  - Physical Education 1950 (Box 25)
  - Physics 1950 (Box 25)
  - Political Science 1950 (Box 25)
  - Printing 1950 (Box 25)
  - Psychology 1950 (Box 25)
  - Purchasing Office - University 1950 (Box 25)
  - Purchase and Printing - State Office 1950 (Box 25)
  - "Q" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 25)
  - Questionnaires 1950 (Box 25)
  - "R" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 25)
  - Radio - WUVA 1950 (Box 25)
  - Recommendation - Letters of 1950 (Box 26)
  - Regional Education 1950 (Box 26)
  - Registration 1950 (Box 26)
  - Religion 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - General 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - Bureau of Population and Economic Research 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - Bureau of Population and Economic Research (Miscellaneous printed bulletins, etc.) 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - Bureau of Public Administration 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - Geographical Institute 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - Institute for Research in the Social Sciences 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - Medical Research 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - National Research Council 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - Naval Research 1950 (Box 26)
  - Research - President's Scientific Research Board 1950 (Box 26)
  - Requisitions 1950 (Box 26)
  - Richmond Area University Center 1950 (Box 27)
  - Romance Languages 1950 (Box 27)
  - Rural Social Economics 1950 (Box 27)
  - "Sa -Sl" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 27)
  - "Sm - Sz" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 27)
  - Segregation [extensive information on Gregory Swanson] 1950 (Box 28)
  - Selective Service 1950 (Box 28)
  - Senate - University 1950 (Box 28)
  - Sigma Xi 1950 (Box 28)
  - Sociology 1950 (Box 28)
  - Southern Association of Science and Industry 1950 (Box 28)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools 1950 (Box 28)
  - Southern University Conference 1950 (Box 28)
  - Speeches and Articles 1950 (Box 28)
  - Speech and Drama 1950 (Box 28)
  - State Board of Education 1950 (Box 28)
  - State Board of Health 1950 (Box 28)
  - Statistics 1950 (Box 28)
  - Stettinius Memorial 1950 (Box 28)
  - Student Affairs 1950 (Box 28)
  - Sullivan Award 1950 (Box 28)
  - Summer Session 1950 (Box 28)
  - Surplus Property 1950 (Box 28)
  - "T" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 29)
  - "U" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 29)
  - U. S. Office of Education 1950 (Box 29)
  - University News Service 1950 (Box 29)
  - University Press 1950 (Box 29)
  - "V" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 29)
  - Veterans 1950 (Box 29)
  - Virginia Academy of Science 1950 (Box 29)
  - Virginia Education Association 1950 (Box 29)
  - Virginia Music Festival 1950 (Box 29)
  - Virginia State Chamber of Commerce 1950 (Box 29)
  - Visitors - Dockets 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Correspondence 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Anderson 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Judge Barksdale 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Black 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Carrington 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Dr. Emmett 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Garnett 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Gay 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Gravatt 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Howard 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Mears 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Smith 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mr. Talbott 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Dr. Trout 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mrs. Wailes 1950 (Box 30)
  - Visitors - Mrs. Willis 1950 (Box 30)
  - "W" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 31)
  - Woodrow Wilson Birthplace Foundation 1950 (Box 31)
  - "X - Y - Z" Miscellaneous 1950 (Box 31)